.
You can do all kinds of fancy stuff with reinforcement
learning, right.
.
So the Kirk's in reinforcement learning is
that the agent is going to notice is learning
agent right it is going to learn in close
interaction with an environment, right. So
the environment could be the helicopter it
could be the cycle right and or it could be
your backgammon board and your opponent all
of this could constitute environment variety
of different choices, so you sense the state
in which the environment is in right.
Since the state of the environment and figure
out what is the action that you should take
in response to the state, right. So in apply
the action back to the environment this causes
a change in the state right. So now comes
in a tricky part right so you should not just
choose actions that are beneficial in the
current state but it should choose actions
in such a way that they will put you in a
state which is beneficial for you in the future,
right.
Just capturing the queen of your opponent
is not enough in the chase that might give
you a higher reward but it might put you in
a really bad position, so you do not want
that I do you really want to be looking at
the entire sequence of decisions that you
are going to have to make and then try to
behave optimally with respect to that, right.
So what we mean by behave optimally in this
case right where we had assume that the environment
right is giving you some kind of an evaluation.
It is like falling down hurts when or capturing
a piece maybe gives you a small +0.5 or winning
the game gives you like hundred right, so
every time you win every time you make a move
or every time you execute an action you did
not get a reward or you did not get an evaluation
from the environment right so it could be
just zero it could be this could be nothing,
right. So I should point out that this whole
idea of having an evaluation come from the
environment is just a mathematical convenience
that we have here.
But in reality if you think about biological
systems that are learning using reinforcement
learning right all they are getting is the
usual sensory inputs right so there is some
fracture in the brain okay that sits there
and interprets some of those sensory input
as rewards or punishments, right so you fall
down you get hurt I mean that is still a sensory
input that is coming from your skin right
or somebody pats you on aback that still a
sensory input that comes from the skin.
And it is just another kind of an input right
so it could choose to interpret this as a
reward right or this as a collision with an
obstacle something is brushing against my
shoulder let me move in right or you can just
take it as somebody is patting my back so
I did something good right so it is a matter
of interpretation so this is a this whole
thing about having a state signal and having
a separate evaluation coming from the environment
is a friction right.
There is created to have a clearer and clearer
mathematical model but in reality things are
a lot messier you know you do not have such
a clean separation, right and like I said
so you have a stochastic environment you have
delayed evaluation.
.
Noisy so the new term that we have added here
is scalar the new term we have added is scalar,
so that is one of the things with the classical
reinforcement learning approaches he said
I am going to assume that my reward is a scalar
signal right so have we talked about getting
hurt and having food and so on so forth what
will all of this will happen mathematically
is I will convert that into some kind of a
number on a scale right.
So getting hurt might be -100 right getting
food might be +5 winning the game might be
+20 right capturing a piece might be +0.5
or something like that, so I am going to convert
them to a scale right and the goal is now
that I have a single number that represents
the evaluation the goal is now to get as much
as possible of that quantity over the long
run, okay make sense right. So if you have
questions doubts stop me and ask.
So mathematically a scalar which is easy at
optimized, not necessarily right I am just
talking about which is like a cost function
if you want to think about it in terms of
in terms of control systems right so this
is like a cost and I am trying to optimize
the cost all right and so for the cost is
going to be vector value then I will have
to start trading off one direction of director
against the other.
So which component of the vector is more important
so then you get into all kinds of separate
optimality and of questions so it is not really
clear what exactly is optimal in such cases
right, so in fact later on I we have a homework
exercise for you to argue for and against
scalar rewards so you can put on your thoughts
then right, so here again let me emphasize
its not supervised learning right in supervised
learning, right.
.
In supervise learning this is essentially
what you are going to see there will be an
input and that will be an output that you
are producing and somebody will be giving
you a target output okay so this is what you
are supposed to produce and essentially compare
the output you are producing to the target
output right and we can form some error signal
right and you can use that error in order
to train your agent right.
You can try to minimize error you can do gradient
descent on their work into variety of things
you can try to train the agent, so here I
do not have a target I do have to learn a
mapping from the input to the output but I
do not have a target and hence I cannot form
an error right and therefore my trial and
error becomes very essential see if I have
errors rate I can form gradients of the errors
and they can go in the opposite direction
of the gradient of the error, right.
And then that gives me some direction in which
to change my parameters and that constitute
the agent, right neither it is going to be
described in some way right the error gives
me a direction right but now since I do not
know a direction right so I just I do something
I get one evaluations I don't know that the
evaluation is good or bad right so think of
writing an exam right I do not tell you the
right answer I just tell you three right.
And so what do you do now do happy with answer
should you change it should he change it in
one direction or should he change it to the
other direction, so what makes it even more
tricky is I you do not even know how much
the exam is out of, so when I say 3 it could
be three out of three it could be three out
of 100 right and or it could be like 3 out
of 18 which is what the class average in level
in the first quiz right.
So it could be any of these things right so
you do not even know whether there is a good
number or a bad number so you have to explore
to figure out a if you can get higher than
three right or three is the best the second
thing is if I can get higher than three how
should I change my parameters to get to become
higher than three it is I have to change my
parameters a little bit that way okay.
I have to change the parameter is a little
bit this way right so if I am cycling wait
I have to push down a little harder on the
pedal okay all I have to push down a little
softer on the pedal to figure out whether
I am staying balanced for a longer period
of time or not I do not know that otherwise
unless I try these things I would not know
this is why the trial and error part, so if
you pushed on a little harder and I say balance
maybe I should try pushing down even more
harder next time right.
So maybe that will make it better and then
there might be some point where into port
so I need to come back so this is of things
which you have to try unless you try that
you do not even know which direction you have
to move in right so this is much more than
just the psychological aspects of trial and
error there is also a mathematical reason
if you want to adapt my parameters wait I
need to know the gradient okay so that he
will need to look, yeah.
The reward is the one that you know that gives
you the evaluation for the output right so
here in the supervised case the error is the
evaluation for the output of the error is
0 then your output is perfect right but then
have a way of gauging what the error is because
you have a target which you can compare right
and from there you get the error so in the
reinforcement learning case the evaluation
is directly given to you as the evaluation
of the output right.
It is not necessarily comparing against target
value or anything you do not know how the
evaluation was generated now you just get
an evaluation directly so you just get some
number corresponding to the output right so
maybe I should have done put an arrow from
the top saying evaluation comes in from there
but that is exactly where it is coming it
is a substitute for the error signal but it
just that you do not know what the evaluation
is.
Of course way differs from the error is minor
differences you typically tend to minimize
error but you are tend to maximize evaluation
right it is also not unsupervised learning
so I'm super learning you have some kind of
an input right.
.
That goes to the agent and then it figures
out what are the patterns for the in the input
right here you have some kind of an evaluation
and you are expected to produce an action
in response to the input it is not simply
pattern detection right so you might want
to detect patterns in the input so that you
know what is the right response to give but
that is not the primary goal right but in
unsupervised learning the pattern reduction
itself is the primary curve so that is the
difference right.
.
So here is this one slide which I think is
kind of the soul of reinforcement learning
right it is called temporal difference so
I will explain it little more detail and in
a couple of slides but the intuition here
right so if you remember the Pavlov's dog
experiment right what was the dog doing it
was predicting the outcome of the bell you
know if the bell rings there is an outcome
that is going to happen is predicting the
outcome which is food is going to happen.
And then it was reacting appropriate to the
outcome right so most of reinforcement learning
you are going to be predicting some kind of
outcome this going to happen since I am I
going to get a reward if I do this or if I
am I going to not get a reward am I going
to win this game if I make this move what
am I not going to win this game all right
so I am print always trying to predict the
outcome the outcome here is the amount of
reward or punishment I am going to get right.
This is essentially what I am trying to predict
at every point right so the intuition behind
what is called temporal difference learning
is the following right so the prediction that
I make at time T+1 okay of what will be the
eventual outcome let us say I am playing a
game right I am going to say I am going to
win now I am very sure I am going to win now
right, so I can say that with a greater confidence
when I am closer to the end of the game.
Then I can at the beginning of the game right
so I have all the pieces set up and if I am
going to sit there and say I am going to win
the game right it is most probably wishful
thinking right but then you have played the
game for like 30 minutes or something and
there are like five pieces left on the board
now I am going to say I am going to win the
game now I say I am going to win the game
that is a much more confident prediction then
what I did at the beginning right.
So taking this to the extreme right so the
prediction I make at t+1 is probably more
accurate than the prediction I make it t,
right the prediction I make a t+1 is more
so if I want to improve the prediction I make
a t what can I do I can look go forward in
time basically go to the next day let the
clock tick over and see what is the prediction
I will make a time T+1 with additional knowledge
I am getting right.
I would have moved one step closer to the
end of the game so I know is little bit better
about the game right I know how the game is
proceeding I know I can may now make a prediction
about whether I will win or lose right and
use this go back and modify the prediction
I make it time t, right T I think there is
a possibility of say probability of 0 point
6 of me winning the game okay and then they
make a move then I find out that I am going
to lose the game with a very high probability.
Then what will I do is I will go back and
reduce the probability of winning that I made
at time T so instead of 0 point six I will
say okay maybe point five or something alright,
so next time I come to the same state as I
was at time T, I would not make the prediction
of 0.6 I will say 0.55 okay that essentially
the idea behind capital difference learning,
right. So it is a whole lot of advantages
we will talk about it a couple of slides down.
But one thing is he said the significant impact
in behavioral psychology and in neuroscience
right so it is widely accepted that animals
actually use some form of temporal difference
learning and in fact there are specific models
right that that have been proposed for temporal
difference learning which seemed to explain
some of the neurotransmitter behaviors in
the brain, yeah. No yeah see at this point
I will be making a prediction about what is
the probability of winning.
And it could be for each of the moves right
if I make this move what is the probability
of finding if I make this move what is the
probability of finding, let us say I make
move two okay and then I go I see a new position
let me open it responds to it and then I decide
oh my god this is a much worse move than I
thought earlier so what I do is I will change
the prediction I make for move two in the
previous state.
You see that the other moves would not be
affected because the only move it took was
two only about that move I have additional
information therefore I can go back and change
the prediction I make for move to alone, so
you still have the ten moves so they are not
changing any of them. Seeing the prediction
is not like I mean if an ideal world you should
be able to take back a bad move right except
if it is a parent playing with the kid I do
not think those things are allowed right.
Infact I when I play with my son we have sometimes
had to remain back all the way to the beginning
it will probably be me asking to do the remaining
not him because he will be drubbing me in
some one of those games but yeah otherwise
you cannot you just make the change the prediction
so next time you play the game it will be
better at it, it not for that game well basically
you are messed up. Or you did well I mean
so whatever it is yeah looking at RL right
so listen look at tic-tac-toe.
.
How many of you have played tic-tac-toe, good
oh you and you put it right up okay good okay
good so in tic-tac-toe so you have these both
positions right and so you make different
moves so in the first this is what I have
drawn here is called the game tree right so
I start off with the initial board which is
empty right and there are how many possible
branches there for people making moves nine
possible branches right.
For excess move there are nine possible moves
I have nine possible branches and then for
each of these I will have like eight possible
I am not sure this is the right TV for each
of this I have eight possible branches and
they keep going right so what we are going
to be doing is essentially trying to this
formulate this as a reinforcement learning
problem, so how will you do this as a reinforcement
problem right.
So I have all these board positions right
let us say X is the reinforcement learning
agent and O is the opponent right so initially
given a blank board I will have to choose
one among nine actions right so there the
state that I am going to see is this black
the accessory goes on the board right and
the moves I will be making are the actions
right, so in the initial position I have nine
actions I make that do I get any reward not
really there is no natural reward signal that
you can give.
Essentially the reward that I am going to
get in this case is if at the end of the moves
if I win I will get a one if I do not win
I get a zero and if I when I get a one if
I do not print I get a zero right so what
is going to happen is I am going to keep playing
these games multiple times right and at each
point right yeah okay so there is a note here
so what is it not say we ought to assume it
is an imperfect opponent right.
Away there is no point in trying to learn
tic-tac-toe why, they will always draw and
the way we are set up the game your indifferent
between drawing and losing so you learn nothing
I mean basically so you will not know even
learn to draw okay you will just learn to
nothing basically you learn nothing because
you can never win right so you are never going
to get a reward of 1 so it will just be playing
randomly.
So it is this is a bad idea so let us assume
that you have an agent that in that is imperfect
right that makes mistakes so that you can
actually learn to figure out where the agent
makes mistakes where the open it makes mistakes
and learn to exploit those things okay, right.
So your states are going to be this board
positions as you can see we give you see a
game that has been played out on the top of
the slide right and the actions you take or
in response to those board positions.
And finally at the end of the game and if
you win you get a 1 if you do not win you
get a 0, right. There are people you lose
a 0 if you draw 1-1 sure you could even know
other things like if you win it is one if
you lose this minus 1 yeah you possibly could
but you probably have to pay a lot of not
of games because the perfect opponent it is
almost impossible for you to start getting
any feedback in the beginning right you will
always be losing.
So it is going to be hard for it learn but
you will eventually learn something yeah it
will take a lot of Missoula will she learn
something if I say that at every point like
at a particular stage the probability of winning
and like you are having to us date so your
storing information for your storing information
for each and every state that you have entered
right so how will it be different from exploring
the proper know like states place every time.
Because after you have done let us say a thousand
ten thousand games or a million games you
really explored a lot of states and you have
to store for each state the probability of
you bidding at that point yeah and all that
so how will that be different from exploring
it again like I know the probability of winning
oh this still I'm not even totally hope you
are going to solve it okay let me explain
that and then you can come back and ask me
descriptions okay if you still have it okay
great.
So what the way we are going to try and solve
this game is as follows right for every board
position I am going to try and estimate the
reward I will get if I start from there and
play the game to the end, right every board
position I am going to look at the reward
I will get if I start from there and play
till the end, now if you think about it what
will this reward connect Connor Tate right.
So if I win from there I will get a 1 if I
lose from that or if I do not win from that
I will get a 0 right, when I say what is the
reward I expect to get starting from this
board position right it is essentially this
average over multiple games it some games
I will win some games I will lose I or I will
not win like some games I win some games I
will not win so what will this expected reward
represent.
After having played many games, the probability
of winning right the reward is going to represent
the probability of winning in this particular
case that if the robot had not been one right
if you had been something else if it had been
+5 that you would have been some function
of the probability of any right after it has
been +1 for winning -1 for loosing and 0 for
draw well it is something more complex.
It is no longer the probability of winning
right it is the gain a expect to get right
how much what fraction of games I expect to
win over the fraction of games I expect to
lose or something like the rate it becomes
a little bit more complex, so that there could
be some interpretation for the value function
but in general it is just the expected reward
that I am going to get starting from a particular
board position okay.
So that is what I am trying to estimate right
let us assume that I have such a expectation
well defined for me right as I say I have
such an expectation well defined right now
I come to us a specific position let us say
I come to this position here let us say I
come to this position how will I decide what
is the next move I have to make, sorry whichever
next state has the highest probability of
ending.
So I just look ahead to see okay where if
I put if I put the X here right if I put the
X here what is the probability of winning
if I put the X here what is the probability
of winning if you put takes here what is the
probability of winning and I do this for each
one of these right and then I figure out which
ever has the highest probability of winning
and I will put the X there alright so that
is how I am going to use this function.
Does it make sense yes it is very important
so this is this is something which you should
understand this is the crux of all reinforcement
learning algorithms right I am going to learn
this function that tells me if you are in
this state right if you play things out to
the end what will be the expected payoff that
you will get right whether the rewards or
punishment or cost whatever you want to call
it what is the expected value you are going
to get and I want to behave according to a
this learnt function.
So when I come to a state I look ahead figure
out which of the next States has the highest
expectation and then go to the state okay,
great how do I learn this expectation. What
is the simplest way to learn the expectation,
this is actually keep track of what happens
this is to keep track of the trajectory through
the game tree that you play a game you go
all the way to the end right so you keep track
of the trajectory and if you win right you
go back along the trajectory and update every
state that you saw on the trajectory.
You update the probability of winning right
is this increase it a little bit or you come
to the end of the game and he found that you
are not one if you go back around the subject
tree decrease the probability of winning a
little bit right alternatively you can keep
the history of all the games you have played
so far right at every after every game has
been completed you can go back and compute
the average probability of winning across
the entire history of all the games in which
you saw that particular position right make
sense this easiest way of estimating this
probability right but the problem with this
is A you have to wait till the game ends right
or you have to store the history of all the
games you have played item in all of these
could be potential drawbacks okay you can
get around the history part by coming up with
an incremental rule but the main difficulty
here is you have to wait all the way to the
end of the game right before you can change
anything along the way.
So tic-tac-toe is easy like how many moves
can you make in tic-tac-toe at best, four
right the fifth one is determined for you
and so it is basically four choices that you
can make right there so and that is easy enough
to remember right you can always wait till
the end of the game and then you can always
make the updates right what if it's a much
more complex situation right what if you are
playing chess.
Maybe you can wait till the end so what if
you are cycling maybe you can wait till end,
exactly he we do not know right this it depends
on where your cycling if you are cycling learning
to cyclonite embedded it is fine when you
are learning to cycle somewhere on the southern
portal road even do not even think about what
end is there right so this is not some tasks
for which you really like to learn along the
way right.
So this is where TD learning comes into it
comes to help wait I do not think I have a
slight anyway and I am not using the fancy
thing where I can draw on the on the projection
so let us see if I can do it here right suppose
I have come here right and from here I have
played at this point I know the probability
of winning is say 0.4 right so I came here
by making a move from this position.
So I said we were here net and we made a we
know that the probability of winning from
here is 0.3 right but I made the move from
here to come here right but here I had thought
my probability of winning was let us say 0.6
then I thought my probability of winning was
0.6 right but then I looked at my next States
and I found that the best one was 0.3 somehow
right so I went there right but now since
the best I can do from here is 0.3 me saying
0.6 here there is something wrong right so
I should probably decrease the probability
of winning from here right.
So why could it be why could it have happened
that I thought that was 0.6 but the best among
the next was 0.3 may be the other 0.4 that
was fully explored all of that the I thing
is so that whenever I came to came through
this part right maybe I one before right that
it so happened that when I went through like
this right initially I would have gone through
like this and played the game and I am the
examples I drew I might have actually won
some of those games right.
So I would have changes 2.6 right but it is
possible for me to get here by playing a different
sequence of moves also right so for example
to come here right I could have put the X
first here and then here or I could have put
the X like I did here I put the X first here
and then here but either way I would have
reached this position right so there are many
combinations in which I could have reached
the same positions right it just to be nice
to these guys right to reach here there are
different orders in which I could have put
the zeros and the X’S right here we are
showing a specific order now 0 first 1st put
here then put here that the x was first put
here then put in it could very well be I put
the X first here and the o first here and
then I put the X here in the O here right
the multiple ways in this thing goes reach
right.
So sometimes when I play those games right
I lost right sometimes when I play these games
I won therefore it turns out that for due
to some random fluctuations right so sometimes
I will when I go through this specific point
and therefore I have a higher evaluation of
winning right but when I went through the
other paths I had a lower evaluation of winning
right but we know that really does not matter
what path you went through in tic-tac-toe
right once your each that point right what
is going to happen further is determined only
by that point right.
So what I can do now is take this point 3
right you should update that 0.6 down so I
am very confident here I think will the probability
of 0.6 right but the best probability I have
from the next stage is 0.3 therefore here
is should not be so confident right good point
that depends on how sarcastic your game is
right so if you are game has a lot of variability
then you do not want to make a complete you
know commitment 2.3 so you might want to say
okay now let me move it little bit towards
0.3 right but if it is a more or less a deterministic
game then you can say okay yeah 0.3 yes sure
let me go to all the way 0.3 it depends on
the nature of the game we will talk about
these issues later there but how far down
is a tricky thing yeah it is misleading it
is called game tree actually but it is a game
graph in this case yeah .
So as I said kid when this is this is an instance
of temporal difference learning so how while
I use the thing to update this is called temporal
difference learning ok so there is one other
thing which is Should mention here right if
I always take the move that which I think
is the best move right now right let us talk
about it I start tab Laura's I never played
tic-tac-toe before right so I play the game
I play it once I get to the end I win so now
what I do I go back right whether I am using
temporal difference learning or waiting till
the end up dating whatever it is I change
the value of all the moves I have made in
this particular game right.
So the next time I come to a board position
what am I going to do I look at all possible
outcomes everything except the one that I
have played will have a 0 right and the one
that I have played will have something slightly
higher than 0 I am going to take that in fact
it will be like how many of you watch the
movie Groundhog Day it will be like Groundhog
Day I will be playing I will be playing the
same game again and again because that is
what happened to give you win in the first
time around right that but that might not
be the best way to play this right.
So I need to explore right so I need to explore
multiple options right so I should not be
always playing the best rest room right and
I should always be paying the best move I
need to do some amount of exploration so that
I can figure out if there are better moves
than what I think is currently the best move
right so tic-tac-toe there is inherently some
kind of noise if your opponent is random right
but if an operand is not random and if operand
is also playing a fixed rule and if you are
playing greedy then you will be just play
a very small fraction of the game tree and
you would not have explored the rest of the
outcomes right.
So you have to do some amount of things at
random so that you learn more about the game
right so here is a question for you when I
am estimating this probabilities of winning
right let us say I have reached here I look
downright and the action that gives me the
highest probability of winning set gives me
a probability of say 0.8 right but I want
to explore right so I take an action that
gives me a probability say 0.4 okay so I will
go from here to another action that has a
probability 0.4 another board position that
has a probability of 0.4 of winning so should
I use this 0.4 to update this probability
or not
know why that you are questioning the whole
TD idea yeah okay any other answer because
you are learning that whether good or a bad
move will be found out I.
Have to update the value of that smooth I
agree to update the value of winning from
the previous birth position was the question
so that 0.4 I will have to change right but
to exchange the 0. 8 that was a question the
0.8 was a probability of winning from here
right I look or whatever the probability say
I had a probability of winning of 0.6 from
here I look at the bottom and the best probability
of winning says 0. 8 but then I take because
I am exploring I would take an action that
has a probability of winning of 0.4.
Right the question is do I go back and change
the 0.6 towards point for or do I leave the
0.6 as it sorry I am exploring rate I mean
this is we may be necessarily be less than
0.8 this will be 0 .4 for that will be 0.6
so the question here is see one way of arguing
about this is to say that hey if I am playing
to win right I will play the best action from
here right then the best action says 0.8 therefore
I should not penalize it for the bad action
which is 0.4 which I did to learn more about
the system.
That is one way of thinking about it another
way of arguing is to say that hey no this
is how I am actually behaving now right so
I should give you the probability of winning
a book about the current behavior policy right
this should not be some other ideal policy
should be about to what I am behaving currently
and therefore I should update it right so
which one is correct first or the second you
do not know what the second you would say
the second one great so all of you can go
right here in your homework answers.
Okay I think this is one of the homework questions
as well right are you looking at the question
I know you are browsing you are not paying
attention to me but can you look at the question
Jasper you do not have network here I see
is our network does not work okay there should
be a Wi-Fi access point called ICS our studio
or something no fine do you
have the question we have the book offline
I do believe this one of the question say
so otherwise make up a question and write
the answer to that so we will feel will make
sure this is one of the questions but this
is something these are this is like I said
I am going to ask you to think about the whole
tic-tac-toe thing and many of these answers
have relevance later on in fact there are
two different algorithms one does option one
and one does option two.
Right so there is no right answer or wrong
answer right answer is depends yeah so yeah
so this is a different things that you can
think about in this but I told you about two
different ways of learning with tic-tac-toe
one wait till the end and figure out what
the probabilities will be the other one this
keep adapting this as you go along right and
both cases you will have to explore that is
it to key part here in both cases you have
to explore otherwise you will not learn about
the entire game so this is where the Explorer
exploit thingy comes in okay yeah great question
different algorithms deal with it different
way that is one of the crucial questions that
you have to answer in NRL.
So it is called the Explorer exploit dilemma
aright so you have to explore to find out
which is the best action right and you have
to exploit.
.
Whatever knowledge you have gathered right
and you have to act according to the best
observations already made right so this is
called exploitation right so the key was the
key questions is when do you know you have
explored enough right should I explore know
or should I exploit now this is called the
Explorer exploit dilemma right and a slightly
simpler version of reinforcement learning
called the Bandit problems okay some colorfully
called banded problems they of course he is
an expert on bandit problems here you can
the Bandit problems encapsulate this Explorer
exploit dilemma.
My god lot of people are turning and looking
at irritable and so this is the next chapter
we are going to look at this so probably in
the next class I will start plunging into
bandit problems in more detail but so this
will ignore a whole bunch of other things
like the delayed rewards you know the sequential
decisions and other things even in the absence
of all of these other complications that even
if I say that you are all your problem is
you have to take an action and you will get
a reward okay your goal is to pick the action
that gives the highest reward.
I will give you 10 actions you are to pick
the action that gives you the highest reward
right but the problem is you do not know what
is the probability distribution from which
these rewards are coming right so you will
have to do some exploration I have to actually
do every action at least once okay to know
what will be the reward even if they are deterministic
right so I cannot say which is the best action
before I try every action at least once if
it is deterministic it is fine I can just
try every action once and I know what is the
payoff right but if it is stochastic I have
to try every action multiple times right.
How many times do you have to try it depends
on the variability of the distribution right
so these are the subtle questions which we
will talk about as we look at the next chapter
in the first chapter in the book the first
real chapter in the book okay there is an
intro chapter which talks about tic tac toe
and a whole bunch of other things and yeah
you ever stop soon not sure they do all of
this yeah so we come back and talk about all
of this later right so I thought I would not
spend enough time talking about the general
background of RNL applications so I put in
a little bit more slides I typically do this
on the board right.
So I will do this on the board when I get
to chapter 3 right and so one thing which
I wanted to tell you was this right there
are you know two classes of algorithms that
we will be talking about so one of them is
based on what is called dynamic programming
right.
.
So dynamic programming how many of you know
what dynamic programming is I expect at least
23 hands out and I having mechanical engineers
putting their heads have not the CS guys really
you know what dynamic programming is something
wrong with your hand then okay fine so what
this essential idea behind dynamic I will
talk again I will talk ass as usual with other
things will well win this in larger detail
the essential idea behind dynamic programming
is you will be using some kind of repeated
structure in the problem right.
So and to solve the problem more efficiently
right suppose I have a solution that I can
give for a problem of say size n right then
I will try to see if I can use that for defining
the solution for the problem of size n + 1
so some kind of a repeater sub structure in
the problems right very rough way of describing
more dynamic programming is right so for example
one way of thinking about dynamic programming
is I have this game tree right so I look at
the values of winning or the expectations
of winning from all of these steps right.
.
I will use these in order to compute the value
of winning or the probability of winning from
the state right so if you think about it if
from here if I'm going to take say n steps
from here how many steps will be expect me
to take n- 1 steps right so I look at the
probability of winning when I when I have
only n - 1 steps left right I will estimate
that first I will use that solution for estimating
the probability of winning when I have n steps
left right so that is essentially the idea
behind dynamic programming and so what we
will do is well we will talk about how do
you use dynamic programming to solve reinforcement
learning problems right.
And then we will talk about various reinforcement
learning methods which are essentially online
approximate dynamic programming you know so
they are they use dynamic programming ideas
but they do not have any knowledge of the
system dynamics right so the P&R other things
become clear later and so all you do now is
instead of having the entire out come.
.
And using that for estimating the probability
of winning here right I am going to just use
one step that I take through the tree right
I use this what happens in this one step I
will use that in order to update the probability
of winning here rights instead of using the
entire outcome right as in dynamic programming
in reinforcement learning methods we will
be using samples that you are getting through
the state space.
This is the TD method in the other method
I explained to win for tic-tac-toe what would
you do your sample will run all the way to
the end right and you use that to update so
this is the two different ways of using samples
here so
if you are doing it for the first time right
first times down the tree there will be no
updates actually because ST + 1 will also
be 0ST will also be 0 the first time we go
down there will be no updates but once you
reach an end then from there you will start
updating the previous day.
So the next time you go down the tree then
it will keep going further up whether in what
the game have lost the game I actually I am
taking the exact outcome that happened in
that particular trial right at that particular
game and I used that to change my probabilities
right but here I am not just taking the outcome
of that particular game right I am looking
at the expected value of winning from the
next board position right so if I wait till
all the way here and I say I won and it take
this in update as T then I will be only updating
it with the fact whether I won or not okay
but if I am updating it from ST + 1 see I
could have reached this T+ 1 multiple ways
before right
When I am doing the update on from XT + 1
it is essentially the average accumulated
over all the previous trails that I will be
using right so if I play all the way to the
end and update it will be with a one or a
zero but ST+ 1 could be anywhere between 1
and 0 depending on what is the probability
of winning,.
So I will be using that value for update that
is a crucial difference I so there are many
different solution methods so there are all
this which are called temporal difference
methods.
.
So these are all different algorithms TD ? Q
learning’s our sector critic so on so forth
and then there is a so of algorithms which
called policy search algorithms and then there
is dynamic programming so will actually look
at each of these classes of algorithms in
the and the next few lectures right these
are all essentially mostly from the textbook
except policy search algorithms which I will
be covering from other material right and
then whole bunch of other applications for
Aaron it.
.
So could they are all over the place as you
could see optimal control optimization company
to combinatorial optimization for psychology
neuroscience so that is not a three since
it was asking is there anyone from biotech
because biotech people do use reinforcement
learning a lot and usually there are one or
two people in the RL class so this is a surprise
or maybe that is that was a bear trick with
this trip according to the economic website
I mean this is gave up in CS 36 and win back
I do not know right.
.
So here is the most recent the hot thing that
comes from came from RL right more game playing
and for a change is not from IBM is from Google
but the company that actually built the first
this arcade game playing engine was called
deep mind and as soon as deep mind built a
successful engine Google bought them right
and so now it is Google deep mind but it is
a separate entity right it is not part of
Google deep mind operate out of London and
they are doing all kinds of interesting stuff
many of the hot advances a very recent advances
in the last year or so in the reinforcement
learning seem to be coming out of different.
So what they did was how many if you know
about this Atari games right everyone knows
about Atari games people are getting tired
really no one has played bat -man yeah how
would how about pong breakout space invaders
come on yeah anyway so what happened was this
is team in University of Alberta ok which
put out this their what they call the LED
arcade learn and I the Atari learning environment
or arcade learning environment which essentially
they allowed computers to play these games
right these Atari games and what the deep
mine fellows came up with is a reinforcement
un engaging that learn to play this game from
scratch I just by looking at the screen.
Okay that is all the input it was getting
just the pixels from the screen they are all
pixels on the screen are given as inputs to
it used to very complex neural network so
it us a deep learning deep network right and
it is considered one of the hardest learning
problem solved by a computer and I believe
it is a one the only computational reinforcement
learning paper ever appear in nature right
so usually is very hard for non natural science
people to publish in nature kind of obviously
it is usually Hartford computer science folks
the population nature but this was totaled
out as a next step in trying to understand
how humans process inputs blah all kinds of
marketing jargon right but more importantly
than anything else about this it is reproducible.
So I told you about I think that is a warning
sign for me to stop so I told you about the
helicopter right so there is basically Stanford
and Berkeley or the two people who get the
helicopter o fly I told me about the backgammon
player is like Jarrett SRO is the one person
who gets the backgammon player to work right
partly because all the input features he uses
in there or proprietary but partly because
has a very hard problem to solve right what
is amazing thing about this Atari game engine
is that this case are very sub code right
you can if you have enough powerful GPUs right
you can set it up here and get it to play
and get a reasonably working engine right.
That plays those places Atari games that's
the amazing thing about it that is reproducible
as opposed to many of the other things other
success stories other success stories we have
had in the past so I do believe I had just
one more slide after this so let us see if
this will work.
.
Okay so if you are any doubts the green one
is the learning agent is it no this just sped
up for you to see you mean it is not like
the game is progressing at the same rate but
you can see the score slow mind you it was
not given a reward okay it is just given the
screen never got to reward for winning ideas
and understand what the pixels on the top
or rewarding and if we give it roars it becomes
cheating right how does it
which is what they did they did they did at
a game over which is misty the Ailey pure
is considered as cheating but they did not
a game over side so the longer you keep it
going the better it is basically nothing this
is getting boring right.
So it is learnt here
so this is a sea quest you have to swim and
then sink down get some things and come up
so sequence is a game that it never learned
to do greatly on and sequence is not something
which it learn to solve well so there are
a few games like this so they initially published
the nature paper I think they had like 45
or 46 out of the 50 ale games they were able
to play well and I think in 43 of them it
had better than human performance and I think
the current state is they have like one game
that doesn't play well right and have better
than human performance in like 48 of those
games or something.
So is this is amazing you think about it right
so these are all lot of references but we
will be using the Sutton and bought Oh textbook
the second edition we there is a pre-release
copy which rich certain this continuously
updating on his webpage right and the very
short introduction to heading for learning
in Tom Mitchell's book and there is a chapter
in Russell and nor wig and if you are interested
in looking at the neuroscience perspective
of reinforcement learning or the history of
how behavioral psychology models evolved to
temporal difference learning you can look
at Diana and Abbott it is one chapter on reinforce
learning you do not have to understand the
neuroscience to understand the RL chapter.
So do not get put off by the title of the
book right and then the more mathematically
well grounded introduction to reinforce money
would be from vs occurs and sickness so apart
from this we will use one book which is Markov
decision processes by putter men that will
use certain chapters from put Roman and they
are just for us to understand MDPs better
motivation process better.